Inventory of the R. Harris Smith papers
Hoover Institution Archives
R. Harris Smith papers
1934-1996
78019
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes (5.4 linear feet)
Correspondence and writings relating to operations of the United States Office of Strategic Services during World War II, and to Allen Dulles and post-war operations of the United States Central Intelligence Agency. Includes research material for the book by R. H. Smith, entitled OSS: The Secret History of America's First Central Intelligence Agency (Berkeley, 1972); and a draft biography of Allen Dulles, entitled "Spy-Master's Odyssey: The Secret Service of Allen Dulles." Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Smith, R. Harris (Richard Harris), 1946-
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
American historian.
Scope and Content of Collection
The R. Harris Smith papers are mainly materials regarding his written works about the intelligence community in the United States, starting with the Office of Strategic Services and continuing on into the era of the Central Intelligence Agency and National Security Administration. Smith was a writer who did considerable amount of research on intelligence-related topics. Included in his papers are interviews and correspondence with members of the U.S. intelligence community, correspondence regarding the research, writing, and publication of his books, and manuscripts for several books, including a published book called OSS: The Secret History of America's First Central Intelligence and an unpublished biography of Director of Central Intelligence Allen Dulles, entitled "Spy-Master's Odyssey: The Secret Service of Allen Dulles."
United States. Office of Strategic Services.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; Dulles, Allen Welsh, 1893-1969.
- Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - A - B - C (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - D - E - F - G - H (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - K - L - M (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - P - Q - R - S (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - T - Z (Box-folder 1: 5)
- OSS Subject File, 1947-1985 (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes research materials and notes on OSS operations, as well as Smith's writings on the topic.
  - China (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Eastern Europe (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Europe (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - France (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Greece (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - North Africa (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Scandinavia (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Spain (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Thailand (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Vietnam (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Yugoslavia (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Research and analysis reports (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Sussex history (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Research notes on the creation of the OSS (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - OSS files (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Footnotes (Box-folder 2: 16-17)
  - "The Secret History of America's First Central Intelligence Agency" manuscript (Box 3)
  - "War Report: Office of Strategic Services,", 1947 (Box 4)
    A declassified report for the U.S. War Department on the formation and efficacy of the Office of Strategic Services.
- Allen Dulles Subject File, 1940-1978 (Boxes 4-10)
  Includes research materials, manuscripts, and correspondence between Smith and potential sources of information relating to his draft biography of Allen W. Dulles. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Research materials on Allen Dulles (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Manuscripts of draft biography of Allen W. Dulles: "Spy-Master's Odyssey" (Boxes 4-8)
    Pieces of various drafts of a biography about former Director of Central Intelligence Allen W. Dulles written by Smith.
  - A - J (Box 9)
  - K - Z (Box 10)
- Greyhavens Institute Subject File, 1970-1991 (Boxes 11-12)
  Notes, correspondence, and documents pertaining to Smith's time with the Greyhavens Institute on researching and improving American intelligence gathering mechanisms. Arranged alphabetically.
  - A - K, 1972-1991 (Box 11)
  - L - Z, 1970-1989 (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous Documents, 1951-1996 (Box 13)
  Miscellaneous notes and documents ranging from papers on intelligence reform to reader responses about Smith's book on the Office of Strategic Services.
  - U.S.-Indochina/OSS reunion, 1995 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - Pieces of Dulles biography manuscript (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Research materials on Dulles and OSS, 1951-1986 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Papers on Intelligence Studies Groups, 1961-1986 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
  - Twentieth Century Fund - oversight proposal, 1989 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - OSS book reviews and reader response, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Marine OSS history, 1989 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - OSS correspondence - from readers, 1972-1986 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Moseley, Ray (Ciano), 1996 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - Correspondence related to OSS work, 1969-1988 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - Harris, Huntington, 1972 (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - OSS correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 13: 13)
  - OSS correspondence - foreign, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - Donovan Papers: Columbia, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 13: 15)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, undated (Reading room workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Available as PDF files. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - 2010 release of records, undated
    - R. Harris Smith note about official history of the OSS Special Operations Branch, undated
    - R. Harris Smith notes regarding activities and administration of U.S. special operations in World War II, undated